I mean, cheap or not, it's the nature of the factory.
If it produces rubbish, you throw it away, right?
I do understand.
Of course, that human review is a bottleneck.
When you're creating a factory,
you know, a lot of the work is on the quality gates.
You know, there's just no point creating a pull request for the human to review.
When that thing is low quality.
My job as a factory creator is to deliver
high quality pull requests where the reviewer is equipped.
I love that word equipped.
My job is to equip the reviewer with all the information they need
The AI Native Dev is a podcast for developers and engineering
leads at the cutting edge of AI and agentic coding.
Join your hosts, Guy Podjarny and me, Simon Maple,
every week as we chat with the most exciting voices in
AI and tackle the biggest questions facing developers today.
This is the AI Native Dev.
Yesterday you were writing code.
Today you're prompting agents.
Tomorrow you'll be running a software factory.
Agentic coding is moving fast enough to give anyone whiplash.
This June, AI DevCon London sold out. Hundreds of developers,
engineering leads and VP's packed in
to hear speakers from Anthropic, OpenAI, Netlify, and GitHub,
cut through the hype and get to what actually works.
This November, we're bringing it back to New York.
Bigger, bolder, and full of people actually building the agentic future.
Three days of real talks, real tools, real answers.
Whether you're directing the agents, building the loops themselves,
leading the teams, or setting the strategy.
Our early bird pricing ends on September 30th,
so make sure you lock in your place before prices increase.
As a podcast listener, you can get 15% off your ticket using promo code POD15.
We have so much planned and we can't wait to have you
join us in New York.
Hello, everyone.
Welcome back to the AI Native Dev.
Today we're going to talk about continuous AI.
And we talk about repos.
And what is the sort of the container for factories or whatever we call them
on that front.
And to dig into all of that we have with us, Don Syme, who is a long
term kind of industry contributor when it comes to programming languages
and how we develop big open source contributor worked a lot on F#,
on various other projects you would have known.
And today a principal researcher at GitHub working on many things the development,
but specifically also kind of continuous AI and agent workflows,
which we'll cover more. So.
Thanks for coming onto the show.
I should also point out you've given an amazing talk at our latest
AI Native DevCon, and you're a big part here of the London community of,
of of development as a whole, but also specifically now as we transform into AI.
So love having you as part of the community Guy.
It's a pleasure to be here, and it's been a pleasure to get to know
you over the last couple of years as you've created Tessl, and
what a wonderful community here in London and also worldwide
AI Native Dev community. I've used your resources a lot.
I've learned a lot from what you've done.
And, you know, really kudos to to kind of create that,
to take that community ethos that was so strong in the developer world
and continue it through the really big shifts
that have been happening in the developer world.
And yeah, I love what you're doing.
Cool. Appreciate that.
And, you know, it's all about gathering brilliant people and giving them a stage
to share their learnings.
So precisely what we're doing here.
So, we're going to talk a lot about, you know, how do you sort of systemize,
if you will, software development in the sort of new era and
you use the term you kind of individually and also at GitHub,
use the term continuous AI when you think about that type of development.
So maybe for starters just define for us a little bit what is continuous AI.
Yeah.
So the thinking is that there's been a bit of a blind spot in the,
in the AI industry, a really big focus on the kind of the use of AI
basically coming from the chat modality, the individual productivity modality.
Of course, we see that with ChatGPT
just exploding in its initial and then all the kind of
productivity enhancements that come around the chat modality.
But we think there's kind of a missing point of view,
which is about collaboration and which is about automation
and which is about situated automation.
And we were thinking about this a lot last year at GitHub,
and we did some kind of thinking about, I think you wrote about it
and we kind of looked well, you know, we already do a lot of situated automation.
And in CI/CD we have continuous integration,
we have continuous deployment.
And then there's this whole range of activities
that people want to do in this continuous modality.
And the continuous modality is just so central
to how we work in the, in the software industry.
That change is happening in this kind of context,
usually the repository,
but there could be other kind of context, the organization or multi repo.
And that means continuous means you're kind of continually folding
in that kind of sense of change and eventing
and difference and sort of incrementally that's kind of happening.
And always reestablishing these crucial invariants like the software
actually works, you know, kind of continuous integration
or the software is correctly deployed in continuous deployment.
And a lot of these things are very they're central
to how we how software collaboration and deployment works.
But equally we want something new, which is also
these subjective activities like continuous documentation.
Writing documentation is a kind of is a subjective activity.
It's not the sort of thing
where the CI/CD kind of concerns are about, like determinism.
We want everything to be exactly right and double check absolutely everything.
Repetition, then sort of insistence that it always happens, like a lack of.
Yeah, and.
Creativity and more consistency. Yeah. That's right.
And but now we have this whole new bucket of things
like we want to continuously improve the performance of our software.
We want to continuously fix bugs.
You know, we want to continually triage bugs
or have every issue labeled correctly within some kind of schema.
We want to continuously look for duplicates in our in our in our bugs.
And of course, you can kind of do this as these things, each as a one off.
But in the end, you're going to have to put them on
some kind of operational, permanent kind of basis in the context of change.
It's so easy for people to kind of blank on that and kind of say,
oh, look, I can I can find the duplicate bugs in my, in my repo.
But you got to make that continuous, right.
You've got to you've got to get that on an operational, permanently
running kind of basis for that to really be a sustained activity.
So we looked at this kind
of collection of things and we said, well, what what really characterizes this is
they're different to CI, different to CD, but they're also similar okay.
And it's that, that, that and that said, well let's partner that CI/CD
and continuous AI and the key things is continuous,
but also kind of subjective and implemented with kind of AI.
And and that's where we landed with that term when we put that out there.
And it kind of seemed to
resonate with people, we kind of captured something
that other people weren't talking about.
And that's that's our. Super interesting.
It's sort of like kind of echo back
a little bit and the things that resonate with me.
So it starts from the sort of the single player to multiplayer move on it.
And then I guess naturally over there weaves into into automation.
Right. Because one extend like we talk about continuous.
But I think what happens with AI
is that it has this jagged edge and sometimes it works amazing.
It sometimes not.
And we have this kind of a hard to determine points in time
in which we want a human to intervene
and apply their judgment, which is clearly a blocker for scaling.
And in that sense, it's similar to continuous integration,
because before continuous integration was non continuous integration, like,
you know, someone manually running it and sort of running the.
System, there was a lot of homebrew continuous automation as well
sort of gauntlet systems or something like your, your PR would run the gauntlet
of your organization and that kind of all came together
into things like GitHub actions and other CI/CD kind of systems.
And we see plenty of homebrew for people,
kind of automating parts of AI kind of workflows as well.
And it's just like, yeah, you know, we we should consolidate that into,
into systematic ways of thinking about it and systematic ways of actually kind of
doing it in.
Practice, performing
so, so, so it has these maybe like two different routes, one one
going from single player to multiplayer and the collaboration element to it.
The other is the automation and sort of do this repeatedly,
maybe starts with sort of homebrew automation and
and doing it and then consolidating those into the sort of infrastructure
that is CI/CD usage style,
but extended and expanded into
the type of actions that AI can now do that's exactly that are,
naturally less deterministic in, in nature.
And so that really leans into not just the automation,
but also the definition of how would you track this activity?
What is a failed build versus a successful one.
How do you continue with that.
Does that.
So all of those kind of bundled into that term of continuous AI.
Yeah. Yeah, absolutely.
And there's another key aspect here which is about bounding the context.
So then we're going to kind of talk about in the context of automation
and bounding the possibilities of what happens in the automation people
conversations about some kind of automated AI often go off the rails,
unless you're actually situated inside, actually some bounded kind of context.
But we're going to do this in the repository with these particular outcomes.
Like it can create a single pull request, it can create a single issue.
Whatever the job of the automation is on each run,
it gets these particular kinds of inputs and doesn't get anything else.
It has a firewall around it and so on.
So to have these kind of bounded, easy
to understand, simple, kind of simplified view
of what are we, what automation are we actually doing here?
And because people are already really familiar with CI/CD automation,
a lot of people use GitHub actions or some other kind of CI/CD systems.
All sorts of people can successfully kind of use those.
It's really a natural starting point for, for saying, hey, let's automate.
Let's like, let's do this together in because we're all doing it already.
And now let's kind of automate some AI
driven, subjective kind of elements of this as well.
And so yeah, situating it there does make a lot of sense.
It's also counterintuitive to a lot of people.
I've got to say, a lot of people listening on this might say, CI/CD.
I don't want AI anywhere near that.
Right? Yeah.
That's like that's my determinism.
And there's a reason for that. Which is it? Yeah.
One of my friends kind of says it's the place where the grown ups are, right.
You know,
it's the place that really establishes that your system actually works as it is.
And a lot of people have plenty of problems with CI/CD systems.
It's not like it's
so important
that it's a major focus for team activity is just kind of get
these invariants established there, get get the green ticks
and get everything kind of checked there.
They use it for everything because it's so useful.
And the thought of adding kind of more subjective activities into that, like
labeling or issue triage or bug fixing, that can be disturbing for people.
And it's one reason that we don't say we're putting AI into your CI.
No no no no no no, we don't do that at all.
It's CI/CD.
They stay as they are.
Yeah. And continuous AI is a separate bucket of things.
You can do none of it if you like.
You can do a lot of it if you like.
You can dial that as you like.
And that's really, really important that we're not marketing with a core
ethos of what CI/CD does and how crucial that is in the industry.
We want people to double down on that because that's
where we really establish software quality, quality in the in the.
Industry, I think so.
So I relate to that.
I think like on the context of, of context,
you know, of like defining context and defining it.
I, I do think that there's a lot of analogies to the world of CI/CD in
that environments are actually a core element of CI/CD as well.
Right?
They move up from works on my machine to something that is defined.
Continuous deployment is about the environment of the production.
And so defining the context is just
just as probably I'm saying it in quotes because it might it's,
it might actually get fairly complex,
just a new type of environment variable for it.
But it's a good it's
a good though to a question I had, which is you use the term continuous AI.
I feel like there's a lot of analogies in the continuous AI narrative
to the world of sort of factories and factory lines in my,
in my own kind of and con talk, I talked about sort of the software stack.
And in one of those paths I was a little bit stuck with saying,
okay, you have models, on top of which you have tools on
top of which you have skills on top of which you have harnesses.
They all kind of compose down.
And then the harness.
It was hard to know what's above a harness.
And I wrote their factory line.
The term loop became popular
like the next week or something, so maybe that's the term on it.
Now you have this continuous AI, but I guess I guess, do you feel those are
just different words or is like a system harness or a factory line or even a loop?
A loop has a little bit of that optimization
piece to it, the same as continuous AI, I guess.
How much,
how much is just the different lens to arrive at the same destination versus
you're defining something different. I think.
I some of those
conversations like are orthogonal
because the shift
that I'm most interested in is this one from the kind of individual productivity
point of view to something which is more continuous and kind of team
and kind of integrated into some particular kind of context.
And so a lot of the things that are kind of getting developed,
like the notion of
kind of loop engineering, you can apply that all in that kind of
continuous AI setting.
The ledger of record might be different because we typically use the repository
and the issues and pull requests is the actual kind of ledger of record of
what happens and maybe some augmenting kind of things as part of that.
Whereas maybe if you're kind of loop engineering on your local dev machine
or something like that, you might be using a different kind of ledger and so on.
But the concepts can actually flow very freely between the two.
And I really like that.
It's like it's, you know,
there's a lot of
conceptual kind of competition in that kind of like what comes next
kind of space in the individual productivity space.
And I kind of like saying, hey, that's not what we're doing.
We're over here.
And yeah, do all of that
to bring it over, like bring over all the good ideas and, and rethink them,
how they kind of work in the like, how what, what the loops kind of mean.
It might be in lots of steps of a loop, like you get to see you,
you set the continuous AI set up
like we have goal traces, for example, continuous goal traces, which once
a day try and make progress towards some particular defined goal.
And each day you get a pull request towards that goal
and you kind of integrate those, but maybe it won't work
on the next pull request until you've done the previous one.
So it's kind of it's not really a is that a loop or is it not a loop.
It's kind of a loop because it's kind of, you know, repeating those pull requests
towards the goal, but it's a cooperative loop
that's actually quite slow in its kind of action.
That might be what an enterprise exactly wants to kind of
to kind of chip away at the kind of all the big backlog of accessibility
bugs or something like that, that, that a product has,
you know, that those kind of loops actually really satisfying for, for teams
where they have like this cadence of like daily improvement
towards some kind of goal that is measurable.
You can see you're making progress
and managers can kind of understand what's kind of going on.
Whereas, you know,
if it's in the kind of loop engineering world
where the individual developer is like,
yeah, I fixed a thousand kind of accessibility bugs, and here's a thousand
pull requests for the team to review, lets you all have to spend all drop
everything you're doing and kind of review those, you know, that that's kind
of a little bit like a little bit disruptive to how teams work together.
So we kind of get to shape things a bit differently in when you
when slow things down a bit, can move in a different kind of pace.
I feel like I
relate
to the the distinction between the single player and the multiplayer.
I think that is very important.
There are still sort of two things here.
One is the, the, the pipeline.
So the continuous AI element of the pipeline, this is a,
an aspiration to get to a point in which you can get a recurring
or like a repeatable motion of getting a type of input
to come into the pipeline and process it and get a certain caliber
output out of it in a repeatable fashion from the.
Maybe it's even two other aspects of what I would what I would say is a loop,
which is more look at how that was done again and again for it and improve it.
So so a self improving pipeline.
So because you can apply a loop to CI/CD I mean in fact we do it you know
and we do it for ourselves.
We do it with the test agent for others which is fix flaky tests.
So flaky tests are an example of, of something that isn't necessarily
a pipeline its own. Right.
Maybe it is, but it is about identifying failures in the CI/CD and fixing them.
But I think that's the loop.
And then I think debatable a little bit on the term factory
where there is proactive initiation
of, of, of a thing, of, of something
that is like an event driven, you know, a bug was reported.
That's probably not its own term.
It's probably like either we're talking about two things,
the pipeline and the loop is actually the initiator
So do you, do you agree with that sort of separation?
We have the pipeline and the and maybe the loop and the initiation of it.
And how does that relate to the GitHub agent workflows,
like the sort of the core capability that is from GitHub?
I mean, what is the scope of that product?
Is it both of them? Is it more? Is it others?
Maybe tell us a little bit about the kind of the product side, you know.
Yeah, yeah.
Because we've talked about kind of continuous AI and I'm very excited
to say the GitHub Agentic Workflows, which is our
of our kind of continuous AI system for,
for, for GitHub actions, is now in public preview.
And, you know, it's going to be part of it is part of the GitHub product line up.
And so, you know, get up there and kind of use that.
So what is GitHub Agentic Workflows.
We think of it as sort of intelligent automation for GitHub at the at the
at the high level.
And that concretely that means you're running
the coding agents, you know, and love the ones you're very familiar with.
You know, your Claude Codes
or your Copilot CLIs or your Gemini CLIs and the like,
and you're running those with strong
guardrails in GitHub actions on.
So that's on an automated kind of basis.
And all of those elements are kind of crucial to us.
First of all,
it is intelligent automation, continuous AI like we've kind of been talking about.
You get a choice of coding agent.
We're not tying you into kind of Copilot though.
Absolutely. That's kind of a difficult one.
It's a wonderful, wonderful coding agent.
And you get the choices of models
and you bring your own key and lots of kinds of things about that.
It's all kind of open source as well.
You can kind of look at it, look at, look at it all.
How it works and with strong guardrails is absolutely key.
And I'm kind of we're going to be talking
more about security and guardrails later on I think.
But you know the better the guardrails are the faster you can run with automation.
It's like train tracks,
you know, the stronger the train tracks, the faster you can run.
This is so crucial.
And so many people are kind of missing this in that in the automated modality,
in the continuous AI modality, you've got to be able to sleep at night.
You've got
to be able to have those things running when you're not there and responding to
things and trusting those kind of things and making sure the that,
making sure all the kind of integrity and information flows
are kind of right and reviewable to check your not kind of leaking information.
So we had Ori from Sierra on the podcast here.
And he pointed out, so like if you
if you allow the agent to do something and you run it enough times,
it's almost inevitable that it would eventually do that thing.
So yeah, that's right.
You need to you got to set the guardrails.
You got to set the constraints really strongly.
And information flow integrity. And
You do need to think about what you're doing.
You shouldn't make your private repositories
kind of accessible to agents running in public repositories.
That's you know, that's just asking for trouble.
You've got to know your basics of agentic security.
And the agentic kind of information flow that people bring in issues.
If you're going to triage, raise issues, you've got to think twice
about about triaging issues from from third parties.
And and we do that mostly through forcing you to opt in
when you do certain actions, like the default
is to kind of ignore issues coming from untrusted contributors.
For example, you've got to opt in if you're an agentic workflow
that's going to process that kind of information.
So that's what GitHub Agentic Workflows are.
Intelligent automation for GitHub are running the coding agents
you know and love with strong guardrails in GitHub actions.
And it's a starting point.
We're going to see a lot of different implementations of continuous AI.
We're going to see we have a thing called GitHub automations as well from
which are more for individual automation automations for individual productivity.
There's going to be a lot of different kind of automated kind of systems.
There's a whole spectrum of kind of things.
You know, this is how we're cracking open the space to say, hey,
you know, that DevOps mentality of CI/CD, bring it along to the party.
And it sounds like, GitHub Agentic Workflows are,
in my analogy, before maybe more of the pipeline than the loop.
So they are the means of interacting it.
They are an event driven system.
An issue comes along or something.
You might trigger that, but they they are not.
They don't.
It doesn't implicitly drive you to create the loop or not.
It's sort of your choice.
Now you can create another
time driven schedule that will now do this on a daily basis.
And so you can do that with the programable sort of system on it.
But it is about an agent pipeline. Yeah.
And you kind of think of it as one step of the loop as well,
like taking the issue and creating the pull request.
Now taking the goal and doing one step of that, taking the backlog
and doing a small part of that and implementing one, five, ten
kind of fixes in one five, ten.
It doesn't have to be one issue to one pull request a single run my create
multiple pull request. It might process multiple issues.
It might do other kinds of work.
It might work off backlog as a source of input.
It might also be a planning step.
It might sort of decompose that kind of it might be a research step.
That's actually a very common way.
It says, hey, here, every day we're going to do some research on
how we can improve performance in this repository.
We're not going to do the work, going to do a lot of investigation of that.
We're going to write a report on like,
what are your top five opportunities for improving performance?
And then the the human,
the maintainer or the contributors can say,
let's break that down and actually take that to the next step and actually
go and implement those, each of those kind of opportunities.
There, actually just do numbers one and three.
So there's kind of like it's a it allows you to create a lot of different
interesting kind of back and forth assistive kind of flows fairly.
They're not they're not super fast kind of flows.
It's like CI/CD, you know, because you're you
really are doing depth research that may involve building the product.
Right.
That may involve taking screenshots and doing research on the product.
And that's where these things are, can be very different
to sort of other kinds of automation you see floating around the industry.
Because we do have the expectation that a lot of a lot
of the time these steps can do real software engineering.
They can build the product, they can run, they can. Take.
They can be working off production telemetry data, for example.
They can be kind of getting the latest
like ten failures off your site and then say, let's prioritize
those and write your research report on how's your site reliability going.
You know, surfacing all this kind of subjective information
into useful and useful reports and actionable kind of work to take.
Things forward. So what?
So that makes a lot of sense to me.
And agents are amazingly powerful and you can run them.
And cloud agents have also become much more sort of useful
as we sort of run those. Right.
So this is sort of situated cloud agents.
And so so that's a that's kind of where I wanted.
So I wanted to
maybe shift and talk a little bit about the sort of the repo as the unit.
So as I think about GitHub workflows, which granted is a
fairly new product on it, I'm sure it'll expand many things.
But one of the things that I feel if I were to explain why is it different?
How is it different than any other cloud agent?
You know,
it feels like a lot of the core of it is just that sort of repo centricity.
And, you know, one of the one of the sentences
kind of in the, in the, in the web pages there talks about turning every repo
into a software factory.
And so I guess it feels to me like GitHub Agentic Workflows are effectively
cloud agents that are kind of repo native.
So they're they get defined in the repo.
They execute with an expectation that all of their activity
and all of that which other agents can potentially also do.
But but it's just like a core element to is that is that right?
Is there is there something. Else that's.
Fundamentally different?
That's right. And that's absolutely
a key
core design decision about where we started with the CI
CD kind of analogies, which are also highly repo centricity, eccentric
kind of flows and automations.
And now and there's a reason
why in that it, there's just so much becomes
simpler when you answer that question of what is the bound of operation?
Where is this running? Where is the definition?
Let's pair that kind of definition.
There are pros and cons to that.
And in the DevOps community, of course, that went back and forth
for kind of many years.
Do the definitions of the automation sit sit with the in the repo or not?
Right. Yeah. There's a whole world of GitOps and.
And on the, on the terminology like the repo as a, as a factory
actually kind of prefer to kind of think of repo as a site of production,
a site where things happen, a site where value is kind of produced
and that might turn out to be a factory, but we produce value in all sorts
of other kinds of ways.
You know, film studio is not a is not a factory,
but it's also a place where value is hopefully kind of produced as well.
So they're all and the the factory analogy is kind of most useful
when there's kind of repeating tasks that are the same,
that are on the pipelines kind of coming through.
But I think we should think quite broadly about since AI has such incredible
breadth of use, we should look for other analogies
and other kind of inspiration that use a factory.
Sometimes that's great, but also use, you know, people.
You do use words like studios or productions or workbenches
and all sorts of other kinds of things that, that, that kind of make most sense.
So there's another crucial dynamic
that in the context of the repo and the context of CI/CD.
And I want to kind of bring this out, which is that
when an organization adopts CI/CD
and gives adopts GitHub or some other similar platform,
what they're really doing is saying to the developers in that organization,
here's a place called the repo, where we, as the organization,
give you the permission to automate within that bound.
Okay, you,
the developers, know best what automation you need for your repositories.
You know best what CI/CD you need.
Therefore, we're going to give you the permission to.
And you can create these things for workflows
which claim some of those capabilities and the ability to create.
Security boundary in a in a decision authority boundary.
Yeah. And but we give it to you. Go for it.
Do what you need to do okay okay.
Maybe we have some organizational guidelines.
Maybe they're reusable actions and so on.
We've got a team that a little bit to make sure
we've kind of keeping a platform centricity in our organization.
But this is an incredibly powerful decision because suddenly
developers have access to a limited form of cloud resource.
They have access to compute, they have access to network,
and they have access to limited
kinds of storage for kind of caching and whatever else goes on.
And that allows developers to be incredibly productive.
And this is why CI/CD is so successful. Okay.
Because there is a bounded context where they can developers
are empowered to claim resources.
They do not have to go and ask the the cloud team in the company
for a new machine.
They do not have to go ask for a budget.
The budget is somehow I'll be measured.
But this is absolutely crucial organizational dynamic.
For why CI/CD is so powerful and so successful.
And we believe that continuous AI
or that AI automation in in contexts will go the same way.
There will be a cost center where this stuff does cost money,
of course, like CI/CD, right?
There will be a cost center where that kind of flows up to there
can be accounting controls because visibility of of where this goes.
There's an authorization context that within that context
we let you use AI according to we still have guidelines and
policies and so on.
But that allows incredibly creative aspects.
And I think this really matters to me in terms of the kind of the jobs
discussion in the industry, because there's evidence that
if you empower people close to the coalface, in a sense
to use AI not though, of course, not an actual coalface.
Metaphorical coalface a little bit more. Yeah.
Because I, I want to.
Hear them.
On real cold faces, I get that, yeah.
But, then they find amazing
productive uses for that for, for these technologies.
And so I'm, I love GitHub workflows because it is an empowering technology
that allows the maintainers of the repos of the people closer up
close to the software to work out how best to use AI.
And you can have incredible conversations about this with people as you start
to unlock, you know, talking to someone working on software for children.
And they say, look, the thing I struggle with is,
is, is that my the language used is getting by, by
is getting written for 15 year olds, but I need it.
I need it suitable for for ten year olds.
And of course AI can make those kind of judgments, right?
AI can read all your documentation strings and all your texts and kind of simplify
the language down and just automate that and do that continuously day in, day out.
It's just like incredibly productive.
I think.
So I agree, but I want to challenge it on sort of the two sides of it.
So I think what we're describing here
is we're saying a repo is a highly convenient unit.
You know, it is it is a space, you know, a production site
in which you can say, I consolidate a lot of my data on the repo.
And because of that, I can define my automation over here.
My code itself sits over there or my kind of other assets potentially
context can sit over there and such, and I think there's a lot of merit to it.
I think also the rise of GitHub actions, which functionally have a lot in common
with other sort of CI systems, which are successful in their own right.
But the sort of the rise of GitHub actions is probably because of that sort of
convenience of sort of being being built into the repo.
So a lot of value there.
However, there are sort of two, two other counter facts to it.
One is the actions that happen cross repos.
So we talk about CI/CD
as though it's one thing, but actually CD oftentimes is not just sort of one repo.
And so sometimes those things become a little bit tricky
and they become another repo.
So suddenly you have those, those paths and maybe even more.
That one is maybe more of a site comment.
And we can get back to it after when we talk about factories as a whole.
The other one, though, is that in the world of AI, there's
there's been kind of this resurgence of the monorepo.
It never went away.
But I think it's it's fairly clear now that a lot of the agents,
a lot of the models have been trained to work in the context of a single repo,
but oftentimes they need information that comes from these other repos.
And so the easiest solution to that
is to consolidate everything into the single repo.
But that starts breaking this
kind of clarity of it's in the same spot because the modern repos can be beastly.
I mean, they can be enormous and they're no longer one thing.
So using a repo now as a unit of access, a unit of security,
a unit of empowerment, of who's allowed
to do what starts really kind of fraying at the edges, especially,
you know, what we're seeing, like we're doing it here at Tessl, which is
fields teams have access to sort of repos and do that because again, it's
so convenient in terms of agent access to pull them in.
But you're kind of losing a lot of that identity of a repo as a project.
Yeah, I think there are.
You've hit the nail on the head.
They're absolutely real tangency.
There's kind of a sweet spot
somewhere in the middle where I like for some kinds of projects,
which is everything works really, really well. And an individual repo.
And we kind of recognize that when we walk up to a repo that's
just the right size and it's perfectly set up for deployment
and everything is working really, really smoothly.
And then there are these other tensions
that are pulling things in various directions.
I think at a GitHub, we have work to do on allowing
making sure that the repo is not the only notion of context
that actually kind of works effectively, that you could have
a collection of repos as a kind of collaborative context,
a friend repos, or whatever kind of features.
You might kind of add to that.
And I, I would, I, you know,
that's one of the things that get discussed at GitHub for sure.
And then there's the question of the organization
as a kind of context as a whole that you could.
But of course, organizations can be absolutely enormous.
And thousands and thousands of repos. And
it's a huge question to kind of scale there.
And even then, some you have enterprises which have multiple organizations
and so on which which adds a new kind of question.
And there are all kind of questions in all of this kind of work.
And you write the coalescing effect into the mono repo.
That was a trend that was before AI.
It is it.
We see it in some projects I'm working on.
I'm saying, hey, look, we should really consolidate these.
It's going to work a lot better if we if we.
Bring it together.
Like it's just no point having these separate.
So yeah, the tensions you say are absolutely real.
And you always see dynamics where people pull things apart
and then they pull them back together and they pull things apart.
And I, I don't have a lot to kind of.
I think it's absolutely work we can do at GitHub to, to tackle,
to give more effective solutions, to stop you being sort of
forced to bring everything into one repo, at least give you more kind
of choice and control about where that's how that works.
And, there would also be the question
of like auth within kind of monorepo.
I'm not really an expert on that kind of thing. I'm.
Yeah. But I get I get that.
Within. Those control.
Hey everyone!
Hope you're enjoying the episode so far.
Our team is working really hard behind the scenes to bring you the best guests,
so we can have the most informative conversations about agentic development,
whether that's talking about the latest
tools, the most efficient workflows, or defining best practices.
But for whatever reason, many of you have yet to subscribe to the channel.
If you're enjoying the podcast and want us to continue to bring you
the very best content,
please do us a favor and hit that subscribe button.
It really does make a difference and lets us continue to improve
the quality of our guests and build an even better product for you.
All right, back to the episode.
So I guess maybe concretely when we talk about the agentic workflows,
what type of automations would you say are sort of suitable
to run within the context of a repo versus which ones are outside?
And when you give, for instance, the example of a repo pulling
in production data and running in it, clearly
the production data is not naturally in the repo.
You know, for, for I think many good reasons.
And that system is elsewhere.
Like you know, that's sort of so that's one example is like,
should that really be a repo level automation
versus something that's outside, like
how would you how would you suggest people start thinking about
what what automation should be done in repo versus which automations?
I guess maybe you technically can do them in the repo, but the there's no.
Even shouldn't.
I, I mean, we, we, we have on the GitHub
workflows sites and really interesting design patterns in this kind of space.
And it's one of the things
I think the team are doing really well is kind of exploring the design patterns.
So there are absolutely cases
where we kind of run a whole zoo of agents in a single repo,
and we've written that up as Peli's Agent Factory, Peli's Agent Zoo.
And like we've got, we've documented like 20, 30, 40 agents there
that are just really, really interesting kind of repeated things that you want
kind of happening in repositories, some really very unexpected ones.
A lot of them are about code improvement.
A lot of them are about like performance.
There are ones about styling, for example, things
that are maybe a bit really subjective and a really bit unexpected,
like, GitHub workflows includes a
GitHub CLI extension, GA
and it has terminal output and we want that well styled.
And it kind of so the workflow runs in the, in the, in the repository.
In this case it kind of runs the the output and checks
runs the tool and checks its outputs and say, hey,
you could kind of make this look better, organize it better.
And that's actually really, really nice.
And a lot of them have got like 70, 80% kind of PR merge rates.
You can start to kind of track the causality of like of the repeating
kind of action and gets kind of statistics.
On like, can I pause on that a second on it. So, so I love those.
And you know, there are many and I highly recommend
people go check out their very, very useful automations on it.
But that's a good example
like the styling one, which is, you know, the definition of that style.
I mean, it could very well
be something that you want to apply to multiple repos, is it not?
Oh yeah. Absolutely.
So yeah, the pattern.
So of.
Course sort of think about it for like where would you then store.
Is that just a reusable action or.
Reusable skills I mean absolutely.
So you import skill libraries right.
So of course
that's again where we a lot of the things
that are kind of emerging in the individual productivity
kind of world, like libraries of skills and Tessl's kind of done work on these.
And yeah, bring them in to your workflows and you can do that directly
and just reference markdown files and or check the skills into the repo.
Is is another thing. If you want to go down.
That's an interesting boundary there of.
So the execution might be defined in it and the skill that you sort of pull in.
But if you want to create, for instance, shared access to system or such,
you might do that through skills.
The skills might sort of span repos. Yeah.
And then there are I guess MCP kind of serve as a similar type of shared access.
So if you want to access the sort of gets managed in different ways.
So I guess all of those, the tools, the context. Of all this.
So to bring in production to me, yeah.
So they're all a part of the continuous AI narrative.
They're just not because the continuous AI is broader than the agentic workflows.
Yeah. Yeah, that's right.
The GitHub workflows can bring in MCP,
of course, and a lot of those kind of things are full of flow.
Flow across.
And you were asking
like when you run things in repo went to run things out.
I mean, GitHub is a very open platform.
You can obviously kind of run automations outside thing outside as well.
A lot of tools integrate with GitHub and that's absolutely great.
I mean, I think our point of view
is to give, you know, there are there are, for instance, data
integrity retention kind of policy kind of reasons why you might not.
Sort of.
Copy them repo outside the GitHub platform.
You've already dealt with, maybe already approved it within your Or.
Yeah, there may be legal or whatever reasons for privacy reasons,
whatever you can and can't kind of take all that issue and pull request metadata
and kind of take it out and then put it back in.
And so it's it's obviously a kind of
we want a credible, powerful default
kind of option to have in GitHub for these kind of workloads.
We do, of course, recognize, you know, lots of kind of depth specialty
security agents or penetration testing or all sorts of other kind of things
that people do that that will have an
happen outside.
Yeah, absolutely.
We do see some people kind of doing a mix where their actual focus
an Israeli startup called HUD is one.
My was talking at
AI Native DevCon, where their focus is on
producing production information, and they kind of need a way to kind of
surface reports about what they're finding about bugs and problems
in product performance results in through production probes.
And for them, GitHub Agentic Workflows is just a really easy way
to do that kind of reporting, kind of regular reporting into the repository
kind of context.
And so in that kind of sense, the main intelligence, the main,
you know, the real kind of systems value add
is actually over in the production probing that kind of gets done.
And maybe some AI processing that happens there and GitHub workflows
just kind of just a secondary role where it's kind of about surface
using some intelligence to kind of surface information that's there.
I think we'll see a lot of that kind of thing.
Using it as a kind of auxiliary utility in other kind of flows
to actually get that information regularly delivered into the repository.
Yeah, it sounds like there's sort of three tiers
over there that you've got information that specifically relates
to the code or other content that your repo holds.
So those are the sweet spot, like finding the automated you kind of
you bring the compute to the data if you will.
Yeah.
Where it is, you have another sort of pair of things in
which a repo might be a convenient way for you to run recurrence on it.
And so the repo is, is just sort of. Yeah.
And you see that pattern often, which is you create another repo
like the whole world of GitOps and things like that are worlds in which the repo is
basically just it's purely a, it's an automation kind of.
That's right on it. Yeah.
That's kind of side repo pattern where you have an automation
running in the side repo, and the target repo is actually some kind.
Of something else.
And in that case, you use that and you get the benefit of
the kind of enterprise, whatever legals and security
and such approvals, if you're already a GitHub user, it's kind of convenient.
Then you might have a third bucket, which are cases in which you need
other sort of optimizations and specializations,
whatever, bursting to a lot of compute or things like that
in which you might want sort of slightly different.
Systems might be applying some proprietary AI knowledge tools.
To do the into into your repository.
And that's kind of going to live off to the side.
The side repo one is actually really useful for controlling
the authorization about about changing the automation as well.
Like who can write
the automation, who can run it, who's the factory runner, in a sense.
And so to have that side repo
targeting a kind of control, a mono repo is a pretty effective pattern.
So should people.
I want to talk a little bit about doing it right
and maybe get into philosophy, but maybe one more tactical question.
When people do the automation, there are sort of these to, again,
kind of push almost like sort of small repo style debate, which is
should you have one workflow that does
multiple things in it, because there's still a bunch of things
you need to configure per workflow and all that.
There's a bunch of convenience to it, to it, or should you have,
I think I guess that's how I interpret the Agent Zoo to be, which is, you know,
I've got 100 different agent workflows that are sort of running on it, I guess.
What's your what's your sort of bias over there?
What's your guidance around.
My, my particular bias is more towards one
workflow which kind of can do multiple kind of things.
One point of cost control, like if you have a
one of
I'm sorry I should say my collaborator's bias, Peli's, is
he is more to have lots, an agent zoo, that's why we call it
Peli's Agent Zoo. And part of that's just exploring the space, like, regularly.
You know, Peli's an amazing guy and we don't want to kind of
constrain what he does.
And you know, we just like just go for it as create as many workflows and and let's
let's see what we let's see what comes out.
Let's learn learn learn.
That's our part part of what we've been doing here.
And but when it comes to actually putting automation, say, into
a repository maintainer for open source
technologies and I don't,
you know, you can create an agent zoo, but that's also a maintenance burden, right?
You know that you've got to maintain those.
You've got to attend to that.
And my attention like span is limited right?
I don't want this to be sucking on my my time.
So I prefer to have kind of one point of attention, one point of kind.
And I also I maintain multiple repositories.
So I'm going to have to look at that across multiple repositories.
Actually, I made myself a little IDE to kind of help with that,
to kind of attend to multiple automations running across.
So not across multiple,
but in multiple automations in different repositories.
And so I
so one example is a workflow I've put together called Repo Assist,
which is kind of a sort of broad spectrum kind of repository assistant.
It like it labels issues for you.
It does first response to issues.
So it sort of researchers issues and responds to them.
It can choose to implement a PR to kind of fix those issues.
It won't merge the PR.
So my regular daily working with Repo Assist is to kind of look, well,
what did it create last night. You know, let's take a look at that.
But why do you what do you prefer that for instance like for instance,
you named there like labeling, researching and an opening a PR
you could have just as well had three different workflows.
Yeah.
So this is in sort.
Of a trigger. Off sort of supervisor orchestrator pattern.
And you can have workflows which, you know, it's a super
choose to delegate up to more powerful models
is an interesting kind of pattern or weaker models for kind of things.
That's important for cost control.
So why do I prefer it?
I think just conceptual simplicity just.
I just it makes my life simpler.
And think about the one entity.
That you just just just to have that
cost control really does matter in this kind of thing.
Complex overall complexity.
I just find having five workflows
considerably more complex than kind of having one.
And how does how does it cost manifest here or.
Oh, so these workflows are very often done in a scheduled kind of way.
So the you may not with issue triage, you have a choice.
You treat each issue as it kind of comes in and do depth research.
All you can do it in batch.
Or you can say each day
we're going to see what new issues will come in and we're going to kind of
catch up in a batch and actually maybe do kind of a batch of them in a single run,
which can actually kind of give interesting kind of results,
as well as it kind of collects information across.
There are things in between that you could imagine having workflows
which kind of have a service policy, which it says,
you know, we're going to triage all issues within half an hour
and, and do three search on, on them within half an hour.
That's kind of a policy.
So then that sort of dictates when how things kind of match.
Yeah.
So now if you Repo Assist is a scheduled workflow.
So you choose the cadence that it kind of is triggered at.
And you hardwire that into the workflow and you have to go and modify the workflow
to change that.
As things currently stand, it's and that's important because you dial up,
you can dial the automation up, you can dial it back down if you're,
if activity is very high in the repo, you can't attend to dial it up.
And if nothing is happening, well, probably you dial it down.
The software is being maintained
and there aren't many issues that are remaining fixed.
Each of those cases, I can roughly estimate how much it's going to cost
like we have now.
You can see in the histories the average cost per kind of run.
It might be in the cents, it might be in a dollar or something,
depending on the models you're using.
And so, you know, you've got a bound, a pretty good bound there and there.
I should add,
there are actually very strong cost control features in GitHub workflows.
I think it's absolutely essential.
It's the thing it's missing from the harness discussion.
I think harnesses should have cost controls and kind of budgeting.
It's absolutely crucial kind of thing.
And again, it's the kind of thing that becomes natural in the automation world.
But it's a little bit unnatural.
Individual additive world. Yeah.
It's also hard to know, when you do the action again and again,
then you can kind of absolutely an assessment and eval
of whether you can run it from condiment metric.
You can. Absolutely.
You can.
We've we've added features that it will do exactly
the same work at exactly the same time with multiple models.
It'll only choose the it will choose, say, the first one as its result.
But you can use turn that on for a day to get like sort of examination.
Testing is what I call it, where you kind of exactly you're doing the models.
A room full of models is doing exactly the same work at exactly the same time,
setting them in exam.
And that really matters when you're using a shared ledger,
because if you write anything to that ledger that hints at the answer
to that, like a closed issue or something like that,
those models will go find it saying, oh, look, I saw another model kind of
did it using this closed pull request or something like that.
Now you've got to test those models at exactly the same time.
So we've got a feature for exactly that, which you can kind of turn on for a day.
And then you kind of get results about like, hey, which models kind of work.
Better. On the in the exams? Yeah. So
maybe let me veer us.
We started talking about costs,
which I would sort of qualify a little bit as like doing it.
Right.
You're sort of running it and maybe I want to touch on, on two other topics.
One is maybe more around autonomy and sort of the risk of regressions.
And as you, as you rely
more and more on these sort of continuous A's and improvement.
And then the second is, is, is safety.
Safety and autonomy are related a little bit
like what is it that it's allowed to do.
So I guess I'll ask the sort of the broader question is, as I, as I lean in,
this is sort of like beyond product, right?
But as one leans into continuous AI and makes changes to the dogs to,
you know, production deployments, fixes,
how how do you know, especially when you think about loops
and you think about systems that improve themselves over time, right.
Gets better and better on it.
How do you how do you sort of see or what do you see
as a best practice for avoiding regressions here?
Do you do you expect every one of these workflows
to generally default to wants to have any value?
If not, like, when should they sort of have evals to sort of know that they're
they're not changing, you know, when do you even define what.
Correct.
And how do you even define beyond vibes.
So what's correct behavior.
Is just to clarify
we're talking correctness for the software or correctness for the agentic
kind of automation. So let me kind of refresh.
So we're talking about automation.
We talked a lot about
how do you sort of systemize the the automation of an AI workflow.
But what we didn't talk about that much is around
the fact that those workflows are non-deterministic.
And so you run them enough times and they might make mistakes,
they might kind of cause problems.
And so I guess what I'm asking around regressions is when we think about CI,
we have some indications.
We know that,
you know, tests will sort of run the test eventually could become kind of useless.
But if they fail, we see it.
We sort of start optimizing them.
And again, it's also like humans have created them.
I think in the world of AI, you give much more sort of vague instructions.
There's a lot, many more degrees of freedom.
And especially if you have a self
optimizing workflow that modifies itself and and improves.
How do you how do you know or like what should you have in place. To.
Keep it from.
To be?
To be clear, in this world, the human is always in the loop.
Okay?
At the at the point of the pull request in particular or the issue.
So an issue gets created or a request gets created
and no pull request gets merged without the human actually approving that.
And that will
and it's also the case that there are limitations on what pull requests
can sort of self modify the the automation.
Okay.
That GitHub actions has some built in kind of limitations about actions
creating pull requests which themselves modify the actions.
And those limitations are in there for good reasons.
For you don't want sort of malicious actors
or somehow kind of mucking with you or kind of CI/CD kind of pipelines.
And some of that thinking does carry over.
And so you can have self-improvement kind of loops.
You can have like them,
they can write new skills or they can update new skills
and so on, which are kind of separate to that kind of system.
But I do want to kind of say that there are
some important kind of controls about how much of that thinking
we kind of bring into this world,
and some of that is inherited from GitHub actions.
But if you just want to dive a little bit, like no pull request
gets merged automatically, but that's not a sort of
that's an untenable sort of destination, right.
Like as you sort of produce and you make more changes,
can humans really review like is there a is there a path
for scaling this that doesn't require pull requests to be automated?
So, that is in some ways a separate discussion.
I mean, in the sense
that for GitHub Agentic Workflows, we have a point of view on that
which is at the human is in the loop, okay.
And the human in the loop, definitely at the point
of the modification of the ledger, not the full ledger.
The some of the ledger can be modified, the issues can be written,
but the actual code and it's always been that distinction.
The code is kind of a kind of golden truth of, of of what's going on.
And we
I do understand.
Of course, that human review is a bottleneck.
So of course you can have agentic workflows and other kinds of AI
automation and all sorts of other algorithmic automation
which do review, review, review.
And when you're when you're creating a factory,
you know, a lot of the work is on the quality gates.
You know, there's just no point disturbing creating a pull request for the human
to review. When that thing is low quality.
You've just got to create as many high quality or quality gates
as possible and automate those to
to reduce the amount of attention you're sucking from the humans involved.
Ultimately, I think you do need, you know, on a, I mean, some products
you could almost like auto merge kind of things.
You can of course use kind of stacked pull requests,
or you could just take one long running pull request.
You can push to a request branch.
Yeah, in an automated way to kind of create
a larger and larger and larger feature so that that is okay.
And that is how some loops kind of work.
And of course we have workflows which get the CI green, for example.
So look at all the pull requests.
Find the ones that are red, work out what's going wrong.
Make the extra approaches. No, not propose.
Actually make the extra push onto the branch
because you're only pushing to a branch.
So we do allow automated pushes to pull request branches for.
And you can usually constrain that down to be pull requests that have been created
by the automation itself. Okay.
So you're really kind of carving down right to a to a subset.
So where the industry and different projects will land,
I mean, there's no one answer to that, but I do get that it is
there is more and more pressure towards sort of kind of automated
kind of full construction of software and automated absolutely everything.
And we don't go in that direction. Where do they.
Wait, wait, wait.
We're being responsible, you know. Yeah. There.
You know, they're guidelines about how
and and absolutely human in the loop is absolutely a core guideline
of what we're doing. Here over the path.
I mean, I think I absolutely understand
the sort of the driver for it and it's safer.
But I'm also very conscious of the fact that I guess when I think about a factory,
I think about a higher level of control plane and really everything
that is in the current control plane that is includes
sort of the modifications of the code should sort of
we should aspire to make it agentic.
And so maybe it is the next batch of questions around saying, okay,
you have kind of continuous actions that are sort
of being done in a collaborative fashion on this sort of shared ledger.
That is the repo. Yeah. And,
and you, you propose those.
And so you've created the, the automation of,
of these activities at some point.
And I think at that point for many organizations is now
there, there are the points in which they already have more changes.
They can accept it at Snyk oftentimes actually
very much so today it's like, hey, the problem is not finding issues.
Like, I have a whole world of issues that I already know a vulnerability is
the problem is fixing it.
Hence the sort of the, you know, kind of, focus from inception
on, on fixing them similarly over here is like the, the, the
if you, if you just got it to the finish line,
but you're not able to get it over the finish line and merged, then
then you just sort of create a review fatigue and, you know, to be, to be blunt,
like people are not necessarily well equipped anyway at that point
in time they haven't written.
No, that's and this and that's.
They're not really able.
That's exactly right.
So some of my work is applying GitHub workflows
to factories inside GitHub okay.
So we have for example a factory for CI performance improvement okay.
Now GitHub is a big product and we and CI takes quite a while to run.
And we want to improve that.
The the CI times okay.
We want to make incremental steady sort of improvement
by finding the long running tests and kind of working out.
Maybe the matrix is a bit big or kind of set up.
It can be become a fixture or whatever.
And that, that,
my job as a factory creator
is to deliver high quality
pull requests where the reviewer is equipped.
And I love that word equipped.
My job is to equip the reviewer with all the information they need
to understand why this is being done.
What are the risks involved?
What are the trade offs involved?
Is this a minimal thing as many quality gate checks on this thing as possible?
Of course, in this context you get the CI/CD quality gates
kind of as a as a number one thing.
Now in this in this particular example, we're trying to improve CI perf.
And actually in this setting you've got the evidence right there in front of you.
You've got a run that was done with zero changes
or the latest run on master or whatever on main,
and then you've got the run that's done here.
And you see, look, the test took 120 seconds there and it took 15 seconds there.
We can bank that kind of improvement. We've got the evidence.
So you, you, you give the evidence
to the to the reviewer, you say, you know, I found it.
And maybe you didn't find the evidence to say
this thing should be closed or auto kind of closed.
This kind of get rid of the trash
off the off the production line because this was the dodgy one.
Throw it away.
It's a lot of throwing stuff away in this kind of world.
Much more than before.
Yeah, you get, you get, you get.
The work has been cheap.
It's easier to throw it away because it was just a guy
that sort of ran along cheap in relative.
Yeah. Or it's just in the night.
I mean, cheap or not, it's the nature of the factory.
If it produces rubbish, you throw it away, right?
You know, the car has got a scratch on it.
You know, throw it away on our next offsite for our our team. I'm.
I want to go visit some real factories with some real maybe.
Maybe film studios or something like that.
How do you how do people actually make stuff?
How do they organize this? How do they tell what's good and what's not?
How do they you know, how many you know?
Yeah.
Let's let's let's let's think about this differently.
I think I have a whole world more of questions on it,
but I, I'm afraid we're sort of like a little bit, a little bit.
Dig into some more things.
Yeah. Yeah, a little bit out of time over here on it.
So, I love first of all, Don, thanks for coming on.
I love the I really, really relate to the sort of the term continuous AI.
And I think, you know, there's, there's
there's kind of a world to define around it.
There's still very much around definitions and.
Nice and nice and world.
I love that.
It's always been my, my, my joy of working in the, in the tech industry.
So it's so super fun, very much like, you know, powerful
kind of new repo centered kind of cloud, cloud agent
sort of platform in the workflows and sounds like a lot over there
that we didn't even sort of scratch the surface over here
and then some sort of forward looking questions on the agentic.
Workflows will kind of get you to the PR what happens beyond
how does it relate to the loops?
And, you know, lots and lots to still explore.
Exciting times.
And yeah, we call it the agent repository automation revolution.
It's I think, the title I use for the talk, and I do think it's
going to be at the center of a lot of what practical teams are doing,
and especially in the enterprise, but also open source contexts.
And, you know, it's great time to be a GitHub.
And indeed it's kind of work.
So having me on. Yeah.
Thanks for joining us. Thanks everybody for listening in.
I do very much encourage you to go watch Don's talk,
which is on on our YouTube channel, the AI Native Dev channel.
We'll put it in the show notes.
It's a really excellent talk.
It actually has a lot more content than what we discussed over here.
It's very practical advice, and I hope you tune in for the next one.
The AI Native Dev is brought to you by Tessl, the package manager
for skills and context.
Your hosts are Guy Podjarny and me, Simon Maple.
Our producer is Tom Dowler.
The AI Native Dev is not just a podcast, it's a community.
And we host monthly meetups at the Tessl offices in central London.
Visit ainativedev.io/community to learn more and I hope to see you there.